1983-0723 Assume your position part II, Lodge Hill Seminar
1983-0723 Prenez votre poste dans la partie II du séminaire Lodge Hill
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Sarva bhi saraghi prabhu mayexari
Sarva bhi saraghi prabhu mayexari
Purna jaya ji vachari
Purna jaya ji vachari
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Jagat vichere upakara sauv
Jagat vichere upakara sauv
Parina jaju jag kachari
Parina jaju jag kachari
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
lthi nirdhana paratra jacha
lthi nirdhana paratra jacha
Sarva dhanacha sachari
Sarva Dhanacha Sachari
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Adhi vyadhi varana varati
Adhi vyadhi varana varati
Paya asha purusha chari
Paya asha purusha chari
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Bhaiyakayataya prabhu zachare
Thank you very much
Merci beaucoup
Somebody will translate Me or...
Quelqu'un va me traduire ou ...
The song is written by a relation of ours.
La chanson est écrite par un de nos parents.
He was a convert to Christianity, but a realized soul, and
Il était un converti au christianisme, mais une âme réalisée, et
he could never cope with the system of conversion
il ne pourrait jamais faire face au système de conversion
and also the way the Hindus were treated among themselves,
et aussi la façon dont les hindous ont été traités entre eux,
with the caste system, and all that,
avec le système de castes, et tout ça,
and he has written very good,
et il a très bien écrit,
some of the very good hymns, I should say,
quelques très bons hymnes, je devrais dire,
this is one of the hymns.
c'est l'un des hymnes.
The song is something
La chanson est quelque chose
I really always used to sing in my childhood very much,
J'ai toujours beaucoup chanté dans mon enfance,
and the theme of the song is like this:
et le thème de la chanson est comme ça:
"The one who has got God,
"Celui qui a Dieu,
or the one who has owned the God,
ou celui qui a possédé le dieu,
why should he have any fear?
pourquoi devrait-il avoir peur?
The one
Celui
who moves about or the one who goes about..."
qui se déplace ou celui qui se déplace ... "
I don't know what is the English word for
Je ne sais pas quel est le mot anglais pour
'extensive travelling'.
«nombreux voyages».
The one who moves about extensively,
Celui qui bouge beaucoup,
for the sake of God and for doing good to others,
pour l'amour de Dieu et pour faire du bien aux autres,
but he does not belong to this world,
mais il n'appartient pas à ce monde,
such a person has no fear.
une telle personne n'a pas peur.
He stands above...
Il se tient au-dessus ...
-the language, Marathi language you see, is a very,
-la langue, la langue marathi que vous voyez, est très,
very intense language, I should say, and it touches many corners
langage très intense, je devrais dire, et il touche beaucoup de coins
when you say one word to it. It's like this one is:
quand vous dites un mot. C'est comme si celui-ci est:
"Adhi Vyadhi Varana Varati Payi Asha Purusha Chari."
"Adhi Vyadhi Varana Varati Payi Asha Purusha Chari."
It means: A person of this caliber is standing above.
Cela signifie: une personne de ce calibre est au-dessus.
His foot is above the sickness,
Son pied est au-dessus de la maladie,
the mental problems,
les problèmes mentaux,
and the death itself.
et la mort elle-même.
But when you say that
Mais quand tu dis ça
such a person has the foot on top of this, means also,
une telle personne a le pied dessus, signifie aussi,
you see, it's meaning is, that with the effect of his foot,
vous voyez, cela signifie que, avec l'effet de son pied,
it can get over it.
ça peut s'en remettre.
It's a double language you see.
Vous voyez une double langue.
Like such a person has his foot on top of all these three things,
Comme une telle personne a son pied au-dessus de ces trois choses,
is the sickness, the mental problems, and the death.
est la maladie, les problèmes mentaux et la mort.
The foot is on top of that.
Le pied est au dessus de ça.
It means that such a person is above this.
Cela signifie qu'une telle personne est au-dessus de cela.
Thus, if you have somebody of this caliber
Ainsi, si vous avez quelqu'un de ce calibre
and the foot touches the sick,
et le pied touche les malades,
or the mentally disturbed people,
ou les personnes perturbées mentalement,
or the dead,
ou les morts,
such a person can raise them higher,
une telle personne peut les élever plus haut,
can take them out of it.
peut les en sortir.
It has a double meaning.
Cela a un double sens.
So the whole theme works out this way:
Donc le thème entier fonctionne de cette façon:
that the person who belongs to God,
que la personne qui appartient à Dieu,
who owns the God,
à qui appartient le dieu,
should not have fear,
ne devrait pas avoir peur,
should not get frustrated.
ne devrait pas être frustré.
I needed it very much today.
J'en avais vraiment besoin aujourd'hui.
Because one side of course, is
Parce qu’un côté bien sûr, c’est
the joy of seeing so many Sahaja Yogis, real Sahaja Yogis,
la joie de voir tant de Sahaja Yogis, de vrais Sahaja Yogis,
not artificial disciples or dramatists,
pas de disciples artificiels ou dramaturges,
but real Sahaja Yogis of very high caliber,
mais de vrais Sahaja Yogis de très haut calibre,
and some of the people who stand on the periphery,
et certaines des personnes qui se tiennent à la périphérie,
have been on periphery for such a long time,
ont été à la périphérie pendant si longtemps,
that's, sometimes is dangerous for Me to see
c'est parfois dangereux pour moi de voir
they will be destroyed.
ils seront détruits.
At this time, you need a song like this
A cette époque, vous avez besoin d'une chanson comme celle-ci.
and in childhood whenever I felt really desperate,
et dans l'enfance chaque fois que je me sentais vraiment désespéré,
I used to sing this song.
Je chantais cette chanson.
It's a very touching song.
C'est une chanson très touchante.
All right?
D'accord?
But word by word I could not.
Mais mot par mot je ne pouvais pas.
I'm not in a, sort of a proper mood I think.
Je ne suis pas de bonne humeur, je pense.
So it's touched Me very much.
Alors ça m'a beaucoup touché.
This is Rutambhara  Pragnya.
C'est Rutambhara Pragnya.
I wanted it very much today.
Je le voulais beaucoup aujourd'hui.
So this morning I was telling you about this new awareness.
Donc, ce matin, je vous parlais de cette nouvelle prise de conscience.
Pragnya. 'Gnya' means the knowledge
Pragnya. «Gnya» signifie la connaissance
and 'Pra' means the awakened knowledge.
et 'Pra' signifie la connaissance éveillée.
Which comes out of meditation,
Ce qui sort de la méditation,
sustenance of meditation,
maintien de la méditation,
and then the Samadhi is the effect of that.
et puis le Samadhi est l'effet de cela.
It's a kind of a fruit ripening.
C'est une sorte de fruit qui mûrit.
When this ripens, then you get the taste,
Quand cela mûrit, alors vous obtenez le goût,
the sweetness of character,
la douceur du caractère,
and then you start seeing around,
et puis vous commencez à voir autour,
how the Nature, the Divine,
comment la nature, le divin,
is sweetly playing with you.
joue gentiment avec vous.
This state must be achieved.
Cet état doit être atteint.
For every Sahaja Yogi, it is important
Pour chaque Sahaja Yogi, il est important
that they must achieve this state,
qu'ils doivent atteindre cet état,
because unless and until you have minimum achieved this state,
car à moins que et jusqu'à ce que vous ayez atteint cet état minimum,
you'll be still in a dangerous zone,
tu seras toujours dans une zone dangereuse,
which, as I told you, upsets Me very much.
qui, comme je vous l'ai dit, m'énerve beaucoup.
So everybody must decide to reach a state
Donc, tout le monde doit décider d'atteindre un état
where you every day see the blessings of God manifesting.
où vous voyez tous les jours les bénédictions de Dieu se manifester.
That means you enter into the kingdom of God.
Cela signifie que vous entrez dans le royaume de Dieu.
This is the kingdom of God,
C'est le royaume de Dieu
in which you are looked after, protected, guided,
dans lequel vous êtes soigné, protégé, guidé,
and properly taken to the place of heavenly bliss.
et correctement pris à la place de la félicité céleste.
Through material manifestation,
Par la manifestation matérielle,
through mental manifestation,
à travers la manifestation mentale,
through financial manifestation,
par manifestation financière,
through relationship manifestation,
à travers la manifestation de la relation,
through so many things,
à travers tant de choses,
and also the natural manifestation
et aussi la manifestation naturelle
by which you see the sun, the moon, the stars, the heavens,
par lequel vous voyez le soleil, la lune, les étoiles, les cieux,
and all the five elements help you.
et tous les cinq éléments vous aident.
This state, all of you must achieve.
Cet état, vous devez tous atteindre.
All of you. Again the word is 'all' of you should achieve.
Vous tous. Encore une fois, le mot "tous" devrait être atteint.
And then only the higher ascent works out.
Et alors seulement l'ascension la plus élevée fonctionne.
Now, "How to achieve this state?" is a common question.
Maintenant, "Comment atteindre cet état?" est une question commune.
Now, the first thing as I told you today,
Maintenant, la première chose que je vous ai dit aujourd'hui,
that you are extremely fortunate people,
que vous êtes des gens extrêmement chanceux,
compared to all the seekers of the world,
par rapport à tous les chercheurs du monde,
who have been, who will be, and who are.
qui ont été, qui seront et qui sont.
Because so many things are,
Parce que tant de choses sont,
which were used by seekers to overcome,
qui ont été utilisés par les chercheurs pour surmonter,
you don't have to overcome.
vous n'avez pas à vaincre.
For example they used to meditate, say,
Par exemple, ils avaient l'habitude de méditer, par exemple
on some name of God,
sur un nom de Dieu,
and the attention would go on, say, repeating the name
et l'attention se poursuivrait, par exemple, en répétant le nom
of, praying to that God,
de, priant ce Dieu,
or thinking about that God and all that,
ou penser à ce que Dieu et tout ça,
but the whole thing would be mechanical,
mais tout serait mécanique,
and always they would jump into some sort of a
et toujours ils sauteraient dans une sorte de
low type of a siddhi, so-called, means they get possessed.
Un type bas de siddhi, ainsi appelé, signifie qu'ils sont possédés.
Those people who start taking the name, say, of Rama,
Ceux qui commencent à prendre le nom, disons, de Rama,
you have seen so many of them,
vous en avez vu beaucoup,
they start jumping,
ils commencent à sauter,
and they start behaving in a funny manner.
et ils commencent à se comporter de manière amusante.
So the attention instead of being, becoming concentrated,
Donc, l'attention au lieu d'être concentrée,
would become extremely disturbed, very disturbed,
deviendrait extrêmement perturbé, très perturbé,
and a funny attention, wobbly-type.
et une attention amusante, de type bancal.
And when they became wobbly,
Et quand ils sont devenus vacillants,
and a kind of a left-sidedness came into them,
et une sorte de côté gauche est entré en eux,
they would go on enjoying it,
ils continueraient à en profiter,
just like a drunkard enjoys.
tout comme un ivrogne aime.
Then such people would weep, cry,
Alors de telles personnes pleureraient, pleureraient,
enjoy their crying, trouble others by their crying,
jouissez de leurs pleurs, dérangez les autres par leurs pleurs,
and they would not have power to overcome that.
et ils n'auraient pas le pouvoir de surmonter cela.
So much they would be possessed.
Tellement ils seraient possédés.
Then another kind who were, say, ambitious people,
Puis un autre genre qui étaient, par exemple, des gens ambitieux,
like we have many scientists, and these kind of people,
comme nous avons beaucoup de scientifiques, et ce genre de personnes,
ambitious people, they would get auto-hypnotized.
les gens ambitieux, ils seraient auto-hypnotisés.
Thinking no end of themselves,
Pensant sans fin à eux-mêmes,
behaving in the most stupid manner
se comporter de la manière la plus stupide
and also they would get possessed,
et aussi ils seraient possédés,
and you can see people like Hitler, and all sorts.
et vous pouvez voir des gens comme Hitler et ainsi de suite.
So many of these people today,
Tant de ces gens aujourd'hui,
who are ruling the world, supposed to be
qui dirigent le monde, censé être
in democracy or, say, communism, or anyway.
dans la démocratie ou, disons, le communisme, ou de toute façon.
Most of them are actually the despots
La plupart d'entre eux sont en réalité des despotes
and that's why the chaos today.
et c'est pourquoi le chaos aujourd'hui.
And a theme like nationalistic-spirit
Et un thème comme l'esprit nationaliste
or something like that they would develop,
ou quelque chose comme ça, ils développeraient,
and try to take the advantage
et essayer de prendre l'avantage
of people's right-sidedness and involve them into wars,
du côté droit des gens et les impliquer dans les guerres,
and all sorts of destructive things.
et toutes sortes de choses destructives.
This kind of attention
Ce genre d'attention
is possible for people who think they are very great,
est possible pour les gens qui pensent qu'ils sont très bons,
say, Hindus, Christians, mostly they are warring people.
disons, Hindous, Chrétiens, ce sont surtout des peuples en guerre.
Muslims... Nowadays the Muslims are all warring, imagine,
Musulmans ... De nos jours, les musulmans sont en guerre, imaginez,
among themselves, that's the best part of it.
entre eux, c’est la meilleure partie.
And the Christians are all warring among themselves.
Et les chrétiens se font la guerre entre eux.
And the Hindus are all warring among themselves.
Et les Hindous sont tous en guerre entre eux.
Like there are only two nations
Comme il n'y a que deux nations
where there is Hindu majority, so called, is
où il y a majorité hindoue, ainsi appelée, est
one is Nepal, and one is India,
on est le Népal et on est l'Inde,
and all the time they are quarrelling.
et tout le temps ils se disputent.
There's not one day passes
Il n'y a pas un jour passe
without hearing some news of some sort of a quarrel,
sans entendre des nouvelles d'une sorte de querelle,
because Hindus won't use the swords,
parce que les hindous n'utiliseront pas les épées,
but a very cold-blooded quarrel is on.
mais une querelle de sang-froid est sur.
So this is the situation.
C'est donc la situation.
In the name of God, again I say,
Au nom de Dieu, encore une fois je dis,
because they started on a very different level,
parce qu'ils ont commencé à un niveau très différent,
and their attention goes left or right,
et leur attention va à gauche ou à droite,
and they develop those siddhis.
et ils développent ces siddhis.
So what have we to do?
Alors qu'avons-nous à faire?
First of all, by God's grace, as I told you,
Tout d'abord, par la grâce de Dieu, comme je vous l'ai dit,
you all are realized people
vous êtes tous des gens réalisés
so your ascent is made in the center,
alors ton ascension se fait au centre,
which is a very, very, difficult thing,
ce qui est une chose très très difficile,
absolutely difficult, no doubt.
absolument difficile, sans doute.
But you should learn to keep in the center.
Mais vous devriez apprendre à rester au centre.
But how to keep the attention in the center
Mais comment garder l'attention au centre
is the problem for many people
est le problème pour beaucoup de gens
who are still not above themselves.
qui ne sont toujours pas au-dessus d'eux-mêmes.
Now when you meditate,
Maintenant, quand tu médites,
try to meditate in a sustained way, first of all sustain it.
essayez de méditer de manière soutenue, soutenez-le d'abord.
Then you find
Alors vous trouvez
that you are getting into the state
que vous entrez dans l'état
of Samadhi, means at a state
de Samadhi, signifie à un état
where you start feeling the joy
où vous commencez à ressentir la joie
and the bliss of God's blessings,
et le bonheur des bénédictions de Dieu,
and then you start saying "O God, what a blessing,
et alors vous commencez à dire "O Dieu, quelle bénédiction,
what a blessing, and what a blessing".
quelle bénédiction et quelle bénédiction ".
Once you have reached that state
Une fois que vous avez atteint cet état
then you have to realize "Who am I".
alors vous devez réaliser "Qui suis-je".
Who are you?
Qui es-tu?
What are you?
Qu'es-tu?
You are the Spirit.
Tu es l'Esprit.
After establishing your sustained attention on the Spirit
Après avoir établi votre attention soutenue sur l'Esprit
you'll develop a state where you'll be
vous développerez un état où vous serez
in a complete state of witnessing with joy.
dans un état complet de témoigner avec joie.
Now those, say, who are here,
Maintenant, ceux qui sont ici, par exemple,
can judge themselves very simply in a way.
peut se juger très simplement d'une manière.
Those who tried to have the best rooms,
Ceux qui ont essayé d'avoir les meilleures chambres,
they must have booked ten days ahead of time
ils doivent avoir réservé dix jours à l'avance
then must have done this, that, to get a good room.
alors il faut avoir fait ça, ça, pour avoir une bonne chambre.
Those who want to have the best food,
Ceux qui veulent avoir la meilleure nourriture,
or the best time, tried to have a position, in the mind.
ou le meilleur moment, essayé d'avoir une position, dans l'esprit.
Face yourself honestly.
Faites-vous face honnêtement.
Sahaja Yoga is an honest endeavor.
Sahaja Yoga est une entreprise honnête.
The best privacy for themselves.
La meilleure intimité pour eux-mêmes.
You all should face yourself.
Vous devriez tous faire face à vous-même.
Then the husband/wife, they want the privacy to themselves.
Ensuite, le mari / femme, ils veulent la vie privée pour eux-mêmes.
This is not the time for husband/wife to be gathered
Ce n'est pas le moment pour le mari / la femme d'être réunis
or for you to talk loudly and move about and have fun.
ou pour que vous puissiez parler fort et vous déplacer et vous amuser.
No, this is meditative time you have come for.
Non, c'est la période méditative pour laquelle vous êtes venu.
Is very short time according to Me,
C'est très peu de temps selon moi,
because people spend thousands and thousands of days
parce que les gens passent des milliers et des milliers de jours
to establish their meditative mood.
pour établir leur humeur méditative.
But in this speedy life
Mais dans cette vie rapide
you have to have intensity to establish.
vous devez avoir de l'intensité pour établir.
So get into meditative mood. Some people feel
Alors mettez-vous dans une ambiance méditative. Certaines personnes se sentent
that they have come for a proper
qu'ils sont venus pour un bon
holiday making and there's no sea here,
faire des vacances et il n'y a pas de mer ici,
so how will they have a swim -- sort of temperament.
Alors, comment vont-ils nager - genre de tempérament.
Those who are not so badly off,
Ceux qui ne sont pas si mal lotis,
would be asking for more comfort,
demanderait plus de confort,
"I couldn't get food, I should have this,
"Je ne pouvais pas avoir à manger, je devrais avoir ça,
the best to be given to my child,
le meilleur à donner à mon enfant,
or to my husband, or to my wife." "My."
ou à mon mari ou à ma femme. "" Mon. "
It doesn't matter for one day or night you sleep,
Peu importe que vous dormiez un jour ou une nuit,
boys together and ladies together.
garçons ensemble et dames ensemble.
If there are children, all right,
S'il y a des enfants, d'accord,
but there's no need, for husband/wife to sleep together
mais il n'est pas nécessaire que le mari et la femme dorment ensemble
in this time when you are meditating all in one room, at all.
en ce moment où vous méditez tous dans la même pièce.
You have come for a very special purpose here.
Vous venez ici dans un but très spécial.
You have paid for it!
Vous avez payé pour cela!
So be meditative.
Alors soyez méditatif.
What I find, everybody was talking loudly.
Ce que je trouve, tout le monde parlait fort.
I didn't find them in that meditative mood.
Je ne les ai pas trouvés d'humeur méditative.
Everybody was thinking they are enjoying here,
Tout le monde pensait qu'ils savouraient ici,
very much nice, good, you see.
très bien, bien, vous voyez.
All these ideas are old ideas.
Toutes ces idées sont des idées anciennes.
The silence must be established within and without.
Le silence doit être établi à l'intérieur et à l'extérieur.
I must say, for this, of course Indians are,
Je dois dire, pour cela, bien sûr, les Indiens sont,
they know all that so I would not say Indian qualities,
ils savent tout cela alors je ne dirais pas les qualités indiennes,
but Australia.
mais en Australie.
Australia, I stayed there in all these Ashrams.
Australie, je suis resté dans tous ces ashrams.
In Sydney we had fifty to sixty people living there
À Sydney, cinquante à soixante personnes y vivaient
every day. I never heard a voice
tous les jours. Je n'ai jamais entendu une voix
or even the movement of the foot till I was there,
ou même le mouvement du pied jusqu'à ce que j'y étais,
when I was there. And I was not there for a day or so,
Quand j'étais là bas. Et je n'étais pas là depuis un jour ou deux,
I was there for about ten, fifteen days.
J'y suis resté environ dix ou quinze jours.
Not even the movement and the children crying, nothing,
Pas même le mouvement et les enfants qui pleuraient, rien,
I never heard a sound.
Je n'ai jamais entendu de son.
This was one of the ways you can control your attention,
C’est l’un des moyens par lequel vous pouvez contrôler votre attention,
that in My presence, what do you speak?
qu'en ma présence, de quoi parles-tu?
What do you say?
Que dis-tu?
You must know the protocol part of it.
Vous devez connaître la partie protocole de celui-ci.
Whom are you talking?
De qui parlez-vous?
You can't make fun, you can't joke.
Vous ne pouvez pas vous moquer, vous ne pouvez pas plaisanter.
I can joke.
Je peux plaisanter.
You can sometimes smile, all right, or laugh sometimes,
Vous pouvez parfois sourire, d'accord, ou rire parfois,
but it has to be done with a weight.
mais cela doit être fait avec un poids.
Whom are you talking to. The reason is,
À qui parlez-vous? La raison est,
I'm talking to you all this,
Je te parle tout ça,
because it's only all this rapport,
parce que c'est seulement tout ce rapport,
all this behavior is going to help you.
tout ce comportement va vous aider.
I'm not going to be helped.
Je ne vais pas être aidé.
I'm not going to be saved,
Je ne vais pas être sauvé,
I'm not going to get My realization.
Je ne vais pas avoir ma réalisation.
It is you who have to gain something out of Me.
C'est toi qui dois gagner quelque chose en Moi.
So try to settle your attention with that.
Alors essayez de régler votre attention avec ça.
I've seen people who stay with Me sometimes.
J'ai vu des gens qui restent avec moi parfois.
Sometimes I deliberately call them to see what's the problem is.
Parfois, je les appelle délibérément pour voir quel est le problème.
Some of them who stay with Me, I find,
Certains d'entre eux qui restent avec moi, je trouve,
become subtler and subtler and subtler and deeper.
devenir plus subtile et plus subtile et plus subtile et plus profonde.
And some of them start taking advantage,
Et certains d'entre eux commencent à en profiter,
taking liberties, then taking a kind of a course of life
prendre des libertés, puis prendre une sorte de cours de la vie
which is so mundane and so stupid
qui est si banal et si stupide
that I can't understand.
que je ne peux pas comprendre.
So this awareness should be within your heart,
Donc, cette conscience devrait être dans votre coeur,
that the time is very important.
que le temps est très important.
You have come here at a very, very important time.
Vous êtes venu ici à un moment très important.
And that when you are with Me,
Et que quand tu es avec moi,
is the most important time, of that important time.
est le moment le plus important, de ce moment important.
Historically this is the most important time,
Historiquement, c’est le moment le plus important,
and take full advantage in the real sense of the word.
et tirer pleinement parti dans le vrai sens du mot.
Some people think if they can get some money out of Me
Certaines personnes pensent que si elles peuvent obtenir de l'argent de moi
then it's a big advantage. All right, you can take it.
alors c'est un gros avantage. D'accord, vous pouvez le prendre.
Some people think if they can take some of My time,
Certaines personnes pensent que si elles peuvent prendre un peu de mon temps,
they are at a very great advantage. All right you can, have it.
ils ont un très grand avantage. D'accord, vous pouvez l'avoir.
Or some people think if they can take advantage of Me,
Ou certaines personnes pensent que si elles peuvent profiter de moi,
sort of feeling ego-pampered or something-
sorte de sentiment égoï-choyé ou quelque chose-
"I m a great lord" and some sort of a thing, you know
"Je suis un grand seigneur" et une sorte de chose, vous savez
All right!
D'accord!
But those who are wise take the best advantage
Mais ceux qui sont sages en profitent au mieux
and the best advantage is the growth within.
et le meilleur avantage est la croissance intérieure.
So the first awareness has to be
Donc, la première prise de conscience doit être
that you are such lucky people
que vous êtes si chanceux
that before you stands someone
que devant toi se trouve quelqu'un
who has the control over all the centers,
qui a le contrôle de tous les centres,
over all the powers or, say, who is all-powerful.
sur tous les pouvoirs ou, par exemple, qui est tout-puissant.
How much advantage you have taken of that
Quel avantage en avez-vous tiré?
is the important thing.
est la chose importante.
Now where I stay there are two places you can say,
Maintenant où je reste, il y a deux endroits que vous pouvez dire,
in England, and in India, mostly,
en Angleterre et en Inde, principalement,
and the contrast I feel English and Indian thing,
et le contraste que je ressens est anglais et indien,
in India the more I have stayed, they become more protocolish
en Inde, plus je suis resté, ils deviennent plus protocolaires
because they have old traditional training.
parce qu'ils ont une vieille formation traditionnelle.
But in England I find, people start taking advantage,
Mais en Angleterre, je trouve que les gens commencent à en profiter,
making fun, joking.
se moquer, plaisanter.
You cannot!
Vous ne pouvez pas!
You see, it is different to please,
Vous voyez, c'est différent pour plaire,
but it is different to be frivolous
mais il est différent d'être frivole
and shallow with somebody so intense.
et peu profond avec quelqu'un d'aussi intense.
For example if there's a tin-board
Par exemple s'il y a un carton blanc
and you take it under the Niagara fall,
et vous le prenez sous la chute du Niagara,
what will happen to the tin-board?
qu'adviendra-t-il du carton blanc?
It won't be able to bear even the slightest shower of that.
Il ne pourra supporter la moindre pluie de cela.
So despite Rutambhara Pragnya, like the sun today,
Donc, malgré Rutambhara Pragnya, comme le soleil d’aujourd’hui,
You must have been upset yesterday, thinking that,
Vous avez dû être fâché hier en pensant que
"Now we have come here, we have to live in the tents,
"Maintenant nous sommes venus ici, nous devons vivre dans les tentes,
and the water is raining",
et l'eau pleut ",
I know many of you must have been.
Je sais que beaucoup d'entre vous ont dû l'être.
But the one who has achieved that state would not be:
Mais celui qui a atteint cet état ne serait pas:
"What is there? If I've to live doesn't matter.
"Qu'y a-t-il? Si je dois vivre n'a pas d'importance.
I'm here for a special purpose.
Je suis ici pour un but spécial.
As long as I achieve that purpose nothing matters to me.
Tant que j'atteins cet objectif, rien ne m'importe.
What discomfort, what all these things happen to me,
Quel malaise, qu'est-ce que toutes ces choses m'arrivent,
I have to achieve that purpose."
Je dois atteindre ce but. "
Some of you people cannot see Me so closely,
Certains d'entre vous ne peuvent pas me voir de si près,
some of you are still not capable, doesn't matter.
certains d'entre vous ne sont toujours pas capables, cela n'a pas d'importance.
What is most important is:
Le plus important est:
"I should achieve that state, I have come here for that.
"Je devrais atteindre cet état, je suis venu ici pour cela.
Not for fun, not for food, not for comfort.
Pas pour le plaisir, pas pour la nourriture, pas pour le confort.
Not for anything, but for achieving a special state
Pas pour rien, mais pour atteindre un état spécial
where I become the Guru.
où je deviens le gourou.
What is my preparation for that?"
Quelle est ma préparation pour cela? "
We have to be extremely careful,
Nous devons faire extrêmement attention,
because the attention of the Divine
parce que l'attention du divin
is not raising you directly.
ne vous élève pas directement.
It is a balance.
C'est un équilibre.
You are all the time in a balance, remember that,
Vous êtes tout le temps dans une balance, rappelez-vous que,
and you have to be extremely careful
et vous devez être extrêmement prudent
how far you go with that balance.
jusqu'où vous allez avec cet équilibre.
So now, how do you develop?
Alors maintenant, comment vous développez-vous?
It's all right, don't worry, about the sun,
Tout va bien, ne vous inquiétez pas du soleil,
I like it.
Je l'aime.
I only called him this morning.
Je ne l'ai appelé que ce matin.
So how do you manage this attention?
Alors, comment gérez-vous cette attention?
Now let us see what are the states of attentions are.
Voyons maintenant quels sont les états d'attention.
Either your attention would be a cunning attention.
Soit votre attention serait une attention ruse.
Anything you see, you see from a cunning angle.
Tout ce que vous voyez, vous le voyez sous un angle rusé.
Many people develop that in an ego-oriented society.
Beaucoup de gens développent cela dans une société orientée vers l'ego.
And moreover if you are sort of possessed by cunning bhoots,
Et de plus si vous êtes en quelque sorte possédé par des bhoots rusés,
then God save you and save others.
alors Dieu vous sauve et sauve les autres.
Like the cunning attention would be that,
Comme l'attention sournoise serait que,
anything you see, you start thinking
tout ce que vous voyez, vous commencez à penser
"What advantage I can take out of this.
"Quel avantage je peux tirer de cela.
How much money I can save", you see.
Combien d’argent je peux économiser ", vous voyez.
It's very, very quick.
C'est très, très rapide.
"It would be cheaper this way."
"Ce serait moins cher de cette façon."
"If I go by this way I'll save some time",
"Si je passe par ici, je gagnerai du temps",
you see, "save pounds", "save time",
vous voyez, "économiser des livres", "gagner du temps",
save everything and save your own Self.
sauvez tout et sauvegardez votre propre Soi.
So just to save you are going on.
Donc, juste pour vous sauver, vous continuez.
The attention becomes cunning when you try to save money.
L'attention devient ruse lorsque vous essayez d'économiser de l'argent.
Save here. Save there.
Enregistrer ici. Enregistrer là-bas.
With your own calculations.
Avec vos propres calculs.
But if you try to save the money spontaneously,
Mais si vous essayez d'économiser de l'argent spontanément,
actually there is nothing to be tried,
en réalité il n'y a rien à essayer,
just it happens that you save.
il se trouve que vous économisez.
But the cunning attention tries all the time
Mais l'attention rusée essaie tout le temps
to be smart about things.
être intelligent sur les choses.
It argues, it gives explanations,
Il soutient, il donne des explications,
"Is it better....?" These days
"Est-ce mieux....?" Ces jours-ci
it's such a cheap, cheap, cheap, cheap, cheap thing
c'est un truc pas cher, pas cher, pas cher, pas cher, pas cher
that you go mad really.
que vous deveniez vraiment fou.
Like I had a ticket to go to America.
Comme si j'avais un billet pour aller en Amérique.
I said, "Don't give Me an expensive ticket, first class, or ....
J'ai dit: "Ne me donnez pas un billet cher, en première classe, ou ....
I'll go by a cheap ticket".
Je vais aller par un billet pas cher ".
So they gave Me a ticket, of such a kind
Alors ils m'ont donné un billet, d'une telle sorte
that, I would never have come back to London
ça, je ne serais jamais revenu à Londres
at least for a year,
au moins pendant un an,
and I would have lost in that American English, I tell you,
et j'aurais perdu dans cet anglais américain, je vous le dis,
somewhere.
quelque part.
So it's so much [they ?] had worked out, you know,
Donc, c'est tellement qu'ils avaient fonctionné, vous savez,
this into that, into that.
ceci dans cela, dans cela.
That kind of a horrible attention is useless.
Ce genre d'attention horrible est inutile.
Leave it, forget it.
Laissez-le, oubliez-le.
With that saving also I've not seen anybody becoming rich.
Grâce à cette économie, je n'ai vu personne devenir riche.
Like you want, I want to go and buy some paint.
Comme tu veux, je veux aller acheter de la peinture.
So we buy some paint.
Nous achetons donc de la peinture.
Then they think, "All right, if you bring it back,
Puis ils se disent: "D'accord, si tu le ramènes,
then how can we return it,
alors comment pouvons-nous le retourner,
what should we do, this, that." Nonsense!
que devrions-nous faire, ceci, cela. "Nonsense!
All the time the mind is on that level.
Tout le temps l'esprit est à ce niveau.
I'll give you an example, the other day
Je vais vous donner un exemple, l'autre jour
we got some paint to paint the glass.
nous avons eu de la peinture pour peindre le verre.
See the subtle part of it,
Voir la partie subtile de celui-ci,
you see, in the gross there is a subtler indication,
vous voyez, dans le brut il y a une indication plus subtile,
and the paint was brought.
et la peinture a été apportée.
And then, it was worth nothing, eighty p (pence) or something.
Et puis, ça ne valait rien, quatre-vingts penny (pence) ou quelque chose comme ça.
All right, I mean I can afford it,
D'accord, je veux dire, je peux me le permettre,
so that's why I bought.
c'est pourquoi j'ai acheté.
If you can't afford don't buy!
Si vous ne pouvez vous le permettre, n'achetez pas!
So they said, "Now we should return" I said,
Alors ils ont dit: "Maintenant, nous devrions revenir" dis-je,
"But why? Now it's come out, now go and return.
"Mais pourquoi? Maintenant il est sorti, maintenant va et retour.
You spend so much petrol going there.
Vous dépensez tellement d’essence pour y aller.
If you want to calculate also it's stupid,
Si vous voulez calculer aussi c'est stupide,
and the time you'll be wasting."
et le temps que vous perdez. "
"No but Mother, you see, ultimately we save two p!"
"Non mais Mère, tu vois, finalement nous économisons deux p!"
I said, "All right,
J'ai dit: "D'accord,
now I'll save a lot of money, and I'll show you how."
maintenant, je vais économiser beaucoup d'argent et je vais vous montrer comment. "
I took that paint and painted many things
J'ai pris cette peinture et peint beaucoup de choses
which looked like glass, or which was stone-like,
qui ressemblait à du verre, ou qui ressemblait à de la pierre,
and the whole thing looked so beautiful.
et tout semblait si beau.
So the mind that is destructive is only calculating.
Donc, l'esprit destructeur ne fait que calculer.
If you have such a mind
Si vous avez un tel esprit
know yourself that you have to get rid of
sachez que vous devez vous débarrasser de
that kind of a calculation.
ce genre de calcul.
Cheap, cheap, cheap, cheap, cheap, cheap, things
Pas cher, pas cher, pas cher, pas cher, pas cher, pas cher, des choses
you should just give up. Keep in the centre.
vous devriez juste abandonner. Gardez au centre.
You should not be, of course, over-indulgent.
Vous ne devriez pas, bien sûr, être trop indulgent.
But you should not be also going for, all the time,
Mais vous ne devriez pas y aller tout le temps,
for this kind of a calculation,
pour ce genre de calcul,
because you are wasting your important awakened attention
parce que vous gaspillez votre attention éveillée importante
which very few people have in this world.
que très peu de gens ont dans ce monde.
Must know that you are realized souls,
Doit savoir que vous êtes des âmes réalisées,
you are not ordinary mundane type of people.
vous n'êtes pas un type ordinaire.
You are special people and you are not to waste
Vous êtes des personnes spéciales et vous ne devez pas gaspiller
your attention in useless calculating money, 'p',
votre attention dans le calcul inutile de l'argent, 'p',
and this and that.
et ceci et cela.
Let's go ahead. What happens, let's see.
Allons-y. Qu'est-ce qui se passe, voyons.
I never calculate you know that, but I live very cheaply,
Je ne calcule jamais, tu le sais, mais je vis à très bon prix,
and you can also do that.
et vous pouvez aussi le faire.
This attention, cunning attention,
Cette attention, ruse attention,
is also a very fussy attention.
est également une attention très pointilleuse.
Here it starts saving money
Ici, on commence à économiser de l'argent
and then, there it is in the evening it must drink.
et puis, voila le soir il faut boire.
So all the saving of p, p, p, p, goes into
Donc, toutes les économies de p, p, p, p vont dans
the gutters of drinking.
les gouttières de boire.
Just sin. The sum total of such a personality is what?
Juste pécher. La somme totale d'une telle personnalité, c'est quoi?
So this mentality has to be controlled.
Donc, cette mentalité doit être contrôlée.
Specially for ego-oriented people are extremely calculating
Les personnes orientées vers l'ego sont extrêmement calculatrices
most surprising it is.
le plus surprenant il est.
But the people like Indians who are not calculating
Mais les gens comme les Indiens qui ne calculent pas
are not so rich.
ne sont pas si riches.
They are very generous, they always have money for Sahaja Yoga.
Ils sont très généreux, ils ont toujours de l'argent pour Sahaja Yoga.
I have had never a problem of money with them, never,
Je n'ai jamais eu de problème d'argent avec eux, jamais,
because they are not so calculating.
parce qu'ils ne sont pas si calculants.
To them, to do for others, not for yourself, but for others.
Pour eux, faire pour les autres, pas pour vous-même, mais pour les autres.
To spend for others.
A dépenser pour les autres.
If they have to come to your house:
S'ils doivent venir chez vous:
"All right, open your heart. Now this is the time to spend."
"Très bien, ouvre ton coeur. Maintenant c'est le temps de passer."
Not for drinking and self-indulgence,
Pas pour boire et se gâter,
but for the indulgence of doing for others.
mais pour l'indulgence de faire pour les autres.
That's their practice and tradition.
C'est leur pratique et leur tradition.
So in this respect, you have to take to that tradition:
Donc, à cet égard, vous devez suivre cette tradition:
"Oh they have come. Let's spend now.
"Oh, ils sont venus. Passons maintenant.
What can we do?"
Que pouvons-nous faire?"
This is the main thing one should understand,
C’est la chose principale à comprendre,
those who are mostly self-indulgent
ceux qui sont principalement auto-indulgent
are extremely miserly people.
sont des gens extrêmement avares.
So the attention which is cunning,
Alors l'attention qui est ruse,
is the worse attention, because you see,
est la pire attention, parce que vous voyez,
cunningness also cheats yourself. It is cunning with you,
la ruse se trompe aussi. C'est rusé avec toi,
and you think, "Oh I've been smart enough, you see,
et vous pensez: "Oh, j'ai été assez intelligent, vous voyez,
I've saved two p".
J'ai sauvé deux p ".
But you have lost your soul.
Mais tu as perdu ton âme.
You are no more a Sahaja Yogi.
Vous n'êtes plus un Sahaja Yogi.
I'll give you an example.
Je vais vous donner un exemple.
I told somebody that,
J'ai dit ça à quelqu'un
"Keep the van down there, go by train,
"Gardez la camionnette là-bas, allez en train,
this van seems to be a horrible van."
cette fourgonnette semble être une fourgonnette horrible. "
And there was a lot of a, you see, explanation,
Et il y avait beaucoup d'explications, voyez-vous,
with both the fingers going on like this to Me, you see,
avec les deux doigts se passe comme ça pour moi, vous voyez,
and I got so fed up with the bomb shells coming on Me
et je me suis tellement marre des obus de la bombe venant sur moi
that I said, to go ahead.
que j'ai dit, pour aller de l'avant.
And the thing fell,
Et la chose est tombée
and the thing got spoilt or whatever it is,
et la chose s'est gâtée ou quoi que ce soit,
is out of order now.
est en panne maintenant.
So they had to do what I was telling them.
Ils ont donc dû faire ce que je leur disais.
Without the bomb shell, if they had listened to Me
Sans l'obus de la bombe, s'ils m'avaient écouté
it would have been all right.
ça aurait été bien.
So your attention should not be on saving material things
Donc, votre attention ne devrait pas être sur la sauvegarde des choses matérielles
and worldly things and all that,
et des choses mondaines et tout ça,
but attention itself must be saved.
mais l'attention elle-même doit être sauvée.
Ask a question, "Where is my attention?".
Posez une question, "Où est mon attention?".
I've seen in the programs
J'ai vu dans les programmes
some people are concentratedly listening to me,
certaines personnes sont à l'écoute de moi,
but some people cannot.
mais certaines personnes ne peuvent pas.
Some are concentrated for a short while,
Certains sont concentrés pendant un court moment,
and some get disinterested after some time.
et certains se désintéressent après un certain temps.
Some are looking here. Some are looking there.
Certains cherchent ici. Certains cherchent là-bas.
So how much attention you have saved is the only concern
Alors, combien d’attention vous avez sauvée est la seule préoccupation
of a Sahaja Yogi. Forget about others,
d'un Sahaja Yogi. Oubliez les autres,
they are all garbage cleaners, you see.
ils sont tous des nettoyeurs de déchets, vous voyez.
Forget about others who are not seeking,
Oubliez ceux qui ne cherchent pas,
who are not of your quality, but you are a quality.
qui ne sont pas de votre qualité, mais vous êtes une qualité.
Now what do you have to save?
Maintenant qu'est-ce que tu dois sauver?
For example somebody is a king.
Par exemple, quelqu'un est un roi.
He doesn't bother of two p being saved.
Il ne se soucie pas de deux p être sauvé.
I don't know baba, these days, I can't say definitely!
Je ne connais pas baba, ces jours-ci, je ne peux pas dire avec certitude!
They must be also doing that kind of a thing, you know, but
Ils doivent aussi faire ce genre de chose, vous savez, mais
what is he bothered to save his grace, to dignity.
qu'est-ce qu'il a pris la peine de sauver sa grâce, à la dignité.
But for a Sahaja Yogi the most important thing is,
Mais pour un Sahaja Yogi, le plus important est:
you must save your attention.
vous devez enregistrer votre attention.
It's called as Chitta Nirodha.
Cela s'appelle Chitta Nirodha.
Nirodh -- is saving of your attention.
Nirodh - est d'économiser de votre attention.
"Where is it going, It's such a precious thing for me.
"Où va-t-il? C'est une chose tellement précieuse pour moi.
Where is it running?"
Où est-ce qu'il court? "
Then how do you save your attention?
Alors, comment sauvez-vous votre attention?
Is through concentration.
Est-ce à travers la concentration.
Concentrate. Try to concentrate.
Concentrer. Essayez de vous concentrer.
Don't allow your attention to wobble.
Ne laissez pas votre attention vaciller.
Gradually you will develop concentration.
Progressivement, vous développerez votre concentration.
You can watch My photograph, it's the best.
Vous pouvez regarder ma photo, c'est le meilleur.
Concentrate, bring it in your heart,
Concentre-toi, mets-le dans ton cœur,
let it be integrated in your heart.
laissez-le être intégré dans votre coeur.
You are lucky people,
Vous êtes chanceux,
you don't have to build up a photograph,
vous n'avez pas besoin de créer une photo,
and then give it up because it is just a Avalambana,
et puis abandonnez-le parce que c'est juste un Avalambana,
means it's just a dependence,
signifie que c'est juste une dépendance,
and then you remove it.
et puis vous l'enlevez.
It's a complete dependence for you
C'est une dépendance totale pour vous
and a load for Me -- of complete joy.
et une charge pour moi - de joie complète.
So when you are concentrating in Sahaja Yoga,
Alors, quand vous vous concentrez sur Sahaja Yoga,
absolutely fully in Sahaja Yoga,
absolument pleinement dans Sahaja Yoga,
then you are controlling, saving, your attention.
alors vous contrôlez, enregistrez, votre attention.
This is one type of people.
C'est un type de personnes.
Then the another type of an attention, what we call,
Ensuite, un autre type d'attention, ce que nous appelons,
are the people who are sort of take a very negative attitude.
sont les gens qui sont en quelque sorte adopter une attitude très négative.
The first are the positive, so called,
Les premiers sont les positifs, ainsi appelés,
so called positive,
soi-disant positif,
who are saving money, saving everything that is useless.
qui économisent de l’argent, tout ce qui est inutile.
Now the second type are the archbishops of all that is disaster,
Maintenant, le deuxième type sont les archevêques de tout ce qui est désastre,
misery, mishaps
misère, mésaventures
This type of an attention.
Ce type d'attention.
If you read newspaper every morning
Si vous lisez le journal tous les matins
you will have an attention like that.
vous aurez une telle attention.
All the newspaper people have that kind of an attention,
Tous les journalistes ont ce genre d'attention,
to find where is the disaster.
pour trouver où est le désastre.
I mean, in a sinister way,
Je veux dire, d'une manière sinistre,
they feel happy there's a disaster.
ils se sentent heureux qu'il y ait un désastre.
I've seen people, "Oh Mother, I came to the seminar
J'ai vu des gens: "Oh, maman, je suis venue au séminaire
but the problem is, you see, there was no water."
mais le problème est, voyez-vous, il n'y avait pas d'eau. "
The attention is in finding disasters
L'attention est dans la recherche de catastrophes
within and without.
à l'intérieur et à l'extérieur.
"What happened?", "There's a disaster",
"Que s'est-il passé?", "Il y a un désastre",
"What happened?" "I lost the pin".
"Qu'est-il arrivé?" "J'ai perdu l'épingle".
Absurd, to have such stupid ideas.
Absurde d'avoir des idées aussi stupides.
They will cry and weep and make everyone miserable,
Ils vont pleurer et pleurer et rendre tout le monde misérable,
"Oooh, I'm so miserable."
"Oooh, je suis tellement misérable."
"What?", "My husband doesn't talk to me",
"Quoi?", "Mon mari ne me parle pas",
or "My child is not with me."
ou "Mon enfant n'est pas avec moi."
Such people are extremely self-indulgent
De telles personnes sont extrêmement complaisantes
as far as their relationships are concerned.
en ce qui concerne leurs relations.
They make everyone like that,
Ils font tout le monde comme ça,
"Oh, the person didn't talk to me nicely
"Oh, la personne ne m'a pas parlé gentiment
and he was this way and that way."
et il était comme ça et comme ça. "
They feel hurt at the slightest touch
Ils se sentent blessés au moindre contact
and by that they think they are saving their emotions
et par ce qu'ils pensent qu'ils sauvent leurs émotions
if not the material things.
sinon les choses matérielles.
Such people are very frightened people to talk to anyone,
Ces personnes sont très effrayées de parler à qui que ce soit,
and anybody says nice things also, they get a fright,
et tout le monde dit de belles choses aussi, ils ont peur,
like this, they'll frown.
comme ça, ils vont froncer les sourcils.
The reason is they do not know what they have to save,
La raison en est qu'ils ne savent pas ce qu'ils doivent sauver,
is not their emotions at all.
n'est pas du tout leurs émotions.
There's no need to save your emotions, you are protected.
Il n'y a pas besoin de sauver vos émotions, vous êtes protégé.
What does it matter if somebody says anything to you,
Qu'importe si quelqu'un vous dit quelque chose,
you are above there, nobody can touch you!
vous êtes au-dessus, personne ne peut vous toucher!
You are wasting your attention all the time
Vous gaspillez votre attention tout le temps
by trying to save your emotions.
en essayant de sauver vos émotions.
There's nothing to be frightened of anyone,
Il n'y a rien à craindre de personne,
because somebody is going to say something, harsh word,
parce que quelqu'un va dire quelque chose, mot dur,
that's why you don't want to do something.
c'est pourquoi vous ne voulez pas faire quelque chose.
Such compromising people, so called,
De telles personnes compromettantes, appelées ainsi,
have not understood Sahaja Yoga.
n'ont pas compris Sahaja Yoga.
There is no compromise in Sahaja Yoga at all.
Il n'y a pas de compromis dans Sahaja Yoga du tout.
It is just like a diamond.
C'est comme un diamant.
Diamond will remain a diamond whatever you do,
Le diamant restera un diamant quoi que vous fassiez,
it's for ever and ever,
c'est pour toujours et à jamais,
it's like that.
c'est comme ça.
So one has to understand that the attention should not be allowed
Donc, il faut comprendre que l'attention ne devrait pas être autorisée
to drift into this kind of an indulgence
dériver dans ce genre d'indulgence
which is of a drunkard,
qui est d'un ivrogne,
that, they are the most miserable people, the drunkards are
que ce sont les gens les plus misérables, les ivrognes sont
Just imagine. They'll be always crying, weeping,
Imagine seulement. Ils vont toujours pleurer, pleurer,
and people would think they are very miserable.
et les gens penseraient qu'ils sont très malheureux.
So what you have to save at that time is your attention
Donc, ce que vous devez économiser à ce moment-là, c'est votre attention
from such indulgences
de telles indulgences
into useless expression of your fear
dans l'expression inutile de votre peur
about your emotions.
à propos de vos émotions.
See now, today they sang the song.
Voir maintenant, aujourd'hui ils ont chanté la chanson.
The song did fill Me.
La chanson m'a rempli.
Completely brought out some of the expressions
Complètement mis en évidence certaines des expressions
which would not spontaneously come out at this time.
qui ne sortirait pas spontanément à ce moment.
But the greatest thing it has done is to remind Me
Mais la plus grande chose qu’il a faite est de me rappeler
that, "You are God. You are not to get frustrated,
que, "Vous êtes Dieu. Vous ne devez pas être frustré,
You have to look after all of them,
Vous devez vous occuper de tous,
and You are powerful.
et vous êtes puissant.
How dare to suspect yourself or feel frustrated.
Comment oser se douter ou se sentir frustré?
That thing which is so much reflecting,
Cette chose qui réfléchit tellement,
like a mirror, I see My mirror
comme un miroir, je vois mon miroir
In the same way you should also
De la même manière, vous devriez aussi
have your emotional understanding
avoir votre compréhension émotionnelle
and the emotion should be a mirror,
et l'émotion devrait être un miroir,
you should see yourself in your emotions,
vous devriez vous voir dans vos émotions,
how you behave, how you treat, how you talk
comment vous vous comportez, comment vous traitez, comment vous parlez
So such people should always keep a mirror
Donc, ces personnes devraient toujours garder un miroir
and feel elevated.
et se sentir élevé.
You are a Sahaja Yogi
Vous êtes un Sahaja Yogi
and the mirror, in the reflection, you should see Me and not yourself.
et le miroir, dans le reflet, tu devrais me voir et pas toi-même.
Sometimes I've an eye that really frustrated with Sahaja Yogis,
Parfois, j'ai un œil vraiment frustré par les Sahaja Yogis,
very much. Then I just stand before the mirror
beaucoup. Alors je me tiens juste devant le miroir
and I say, "Now, come along.
et je dis: "Maintenant, viens.
You are the one who has all the powers,
Vous êtes celui qui a tous les pouvoirs,
who has all the chakras awakened.
qui a réveillé tous les chakras.
None of the Advents had this.
Aucun des Advents n'avait cela.
You are the one who has created this world
Vous êtes celui qui a créé ce monde
and You are the one who has to save it. So now, get up."
et vous êtes celui qui doit le sauver. Alors maintenant, lève-toi. "
Not to lose courage,
Ne pas perdre courage,
not to worry.
ne pas s'inquiéter.
Only in the emotional things I sometimes
Seulement dans les choses émotionnelles je parfois
feel that now I'll have to give up some of them, completely.
sentir que maintenant je vais devoir abandonner certains d'entre eux, complètement.
They are My children, as a Mother, not as a Guru.
Ce sont mes enfants, en tant que mère, pas en tant que gourou.
For a Guru they don't have problem.
Pour un gourou, ils n'ont pas de problème.
And then the stirring up comes in, within Myself that,
Et puis l'agitation arrive, en moi-même,
"No, even if I have to give up, doesn't matter, I have to raise,
"Non, même si je dois abandonner, peu importe, je dois élever,
absolutely", and with that power it works.
absolument ", et avec ce pouvoir cela fonctionne.
So the reflection should be of Me,
Donc, la réflexion devrait être de moi,
of something that is ideal before you,
de quelque chose qui est idéal devant vous,
the one that gives you energy, like this song
celui qui vous donne de l'énergie, comme cette chanson
and not the reflection of a miserable person.
et non le reflet d'une personne misérable.
Christ who's standing before you
Christ qui est debout devant toi
as in the Sistine Chapel and not some miserable skeleton
comme dans la chapelle Sixtine et non un squelette misérable
which is even worse than you.
ce qui est encore pire que toi.
So create those images of your Mother
Alors créez ces images de votre mère
which you should see in your emotions and rise.
que vous devriez voir dans vos émotions et augmenter.
This is the second type of attention you have to control.
C'est le deuxième type d'attention que vous devez contrôler.
The third one is a very horrid idiotic one.
Le troisième est un idiot très horrible.
The idiotic one comes from the second type,
L'idiot vient du deuxième type,
where the person is emotionally indulgent.
où la personne est émotionnellement indulgent.
That is the "A" of the third.
C'est le "A" de la troisième.
And the "B" of the third comes from the first type,
Et le "B" du troisième provient du premier type,
which is stupid. So we have two types of people,
ce qui est stupide. Nous avons donc deux types de personnes,
one idiotic and another are stupid.
un idiot et un autre sont stupides.
But in Indian language there's only one word,
Mais dans la langue indienne, il n'y a qu'un seul mot,
specially in Marathi -- is murkha.
spécialement en marathi - is murkha.
For them both categories are the same,
Pour eux les deux catégories sont les mêmes,
as if the circle meets at the same point.
comme si le cercle se rencontrait au même point.
I mean English language in some ways is good
Je veux dire que la langue anglaise est bonne à certains égards
at least it differentiates between the murkhas,
au moins il différencie les murkhas,
like they can be stupid or they can be idiotic, you see.
comme ils peuvent être stupides ou ils peuvent être idiots, vous voyez.
Because of psyche being so confused here,
Parce que la psyché est si confuse ici,
that psychologists have brought out. Some are schizophrenic,
que les psychologues ont mis en évidence. Certains sont schizophrènes,
some are idiots, some are stupid, some are donkeys.
certains sont des idiots, certains sont stupides, d'autres sont des ânes.
So this, the third type is the worst, is most frustrating for Me.
Donc, ceci, le troisième type est le pire, est le plus frustrant pour Moi.
They'll stick onto Me like leeches,
Ils se collent à moi comme des sangsues,
they'll be saying stupid things all the time.
ils vont dire des bêtises tout le temps.
Just can't bear an idiot, isn't it?
Ne peut pas supporter un idiot, n'est-ce pas?
They can bore a person. I mean all sorts of this put together
Ils peuvent ennuyer une personne. Je veux dire toutes sortes de choses réunies
is called as murkha.
s'appelle comme murkha.
So I don't want to analyze it, it's a bit too much.
Donc, je ne veux pas analyser, c'est un peu trop.
So that kind of an attention you have, then you better keep quiet.
Donc, ce genre d'attention que vous avez, alors vous feriez mieux de vous taire.
Don't talk. Just listen to others what they talk, what they say.
Ne parlez pas. Il suffit d'écouter les autres ce qu'ils parlent, ce qu'ils disent.
There are some people who will just go on talking, talking, talking,
Il y a des gens qui vont juste continuer à parler, parler, parler,
irrelevantly, uselessly, wasting their energy,
inutile, gaspillant leur énergie,
and such people are always friends of the cunning.
et de telles personnes sont toujours des amis de la ruse.
The cunning and such people go hand in hand,
La ruse et ces gens vont de pair,
because the cunning wants to befool someone,
parce que la ruse veut tromper quelqu'un,
and the fool wants to be befooled.
et le fou veut être duper.
Like a king will have a jester,
Comme un roi aura un bouffon,
it's like that you see, these combinations work out.
c'est comme ça que vous voyez, ces combinaisons fonctionnent.
So for such people the best thing is to keep quiet.
Donc, pour ces personnes, la meilleure chose à faire est de rester silencieux.
Preserve all their attention,
Conserver toute leur attention,
all their energies just for cleansing.
toutes leurs énergies juste pour le nettoyage.
All this idiocity will pass away very soon
Toute cette idiotie disparaîtra très bientôt
if you try to preserve yourself. Don't talk,
si vous essayez de vous préserver. Ne parle pas,
don't say things which are stupid,
ne dites pas de bêtises,
which are idiotic, just keep quiet, and watch others.
qui sont idiotes, restez silencieux et observez les autres.
Sometimes such people can become very great vehicle
Parfois, de telles personnes peuvent devenir un très bon véhicule
of God's power,
de la puissance de Dieu,
but if they do not take to stupidity and idiocy.
mais s'ils ne prennent pas à la stupidité et à l'idiotie.
This is the type of people, three types I would say,
C'est le type de personnes, trois types je dirais,
but the fourth type are the people who lead a life of concentration.
mais le quatrième type sont les personnes qui mènent une vie de concentration.
I mean a person who is working very hard,
Je veux dire une personne qui travaille très fort,
say, in the office, is a very remarkably successful person,
dire, dans le bureau, est une personne très remarquablement réussie,
and this and that, and that, and that, and that,
et ceci et cela, et cela, et cela, et cela,
is also very concentrated.
est également très concentré.
Somebody who works very well, anywhere,
Quelqu'un qui travaille très bien, n'importe où,
with a concentrated mind, is concentrated.
avec un esprit concentré, est concentré.
A housewife who looks after her husband and children is very concentrated,
Une femme au foyer qui s’occupe de son mari et de ses enfants est très concentrée,
and a husband who looks after his family
et un mari qui s'occupe de sa famille
and his things in a very concentrated way.
et ses affaires d'une manière très concentrée.
They know how to paint well, they know how to do things,
Ils savent bien peindre, ils savent faire les choses,
and their hands are deft, and they know everything.
et leurs mains sont habiles, et ils savent tout.
But such people can have a very immobile attention,
Mais ces personnes peuvent avoir une attention très immobile,
very immobile, like plastic,
très immobile, comme du plastique,
or you can call it, like rubber.
ou vous pouvez l'appeler, comme le caoutchouc.
At the most, to improve on it, we can say,
Au mieux, pour l'améliorer, on peut dire,
like some of the things I have seen which you use
comme certaines des choses que j'ai vues et que vous utilisez
for damp-proofing, you see,
pour l'étanchéité, voyez-vous,
you just apply it, after some time it's just parched, into it.
vous appliquez-le simplement, après un certain temps, il est simplement desséché.
They just can't get out of it.
Ils ne peuvent tout simplement pas s'en sortir.
They just can't. They can't enjoy anything.
Ils ne peuvent tout simplement pas. Ils ne peuvent rien apprécier.
Unless and until you show them a file you can't talk to them.
À moins que et jusqu'à ce que vous leur montriez un fichier, vous ne pouvez pas leur parler.
You see, if you have to talk to such a person,
Vous voyez, si vous devez parler à une telle personne,
better take a file before you,
mieux prendre un dossier devant vous,
and before starting you put the file before you.
et avant de commencer, vous mettez le fichier devant vous.
If it is on the file only, they will see,
Si c'est sur le fichier seulement, ils verront,
but if you talk, they say, "Make a file."
mais si vous parlez, ils disent: "Faites un fichier."
Very parched, and they cannot enjoy life.
Très aride, et ils ne peuvent pas profiter de la vie.
There's no mobility, they cannot be creative.
Il n'y a pas de mobilité, ils ne peuvent pas être créatifs.
They can be creative only as far as their style is concerned,
Ils ne peuvent être créatifs que dans la mesure où leur style est concerné,
but not the creative of the joy.
mais pas le créateur de la joie.
So that kind of concentration is there,
Donc, ce genre de concentration est là,
concentrated effort people put in.
effort concentré les gens mis en po
Like there are people who are fanatics.
Comme s'il y avait des fanatiques.
They are very concentrated in their effort, extremely.
Ils sont très concentrés dans leurs efforts, extrêmement.
That's how all these religions have spread, like Christianity,
Voilà comment toutes ces religions se sont répandues, comme le christianisme,
Islam, Hinduism and all that,
L'islam, l'hindouisme et tout ça,
because they had a concentrated effort of fanaticism
parce qu'ils avaient un effort concentré de fanatisme
concentrated effort.
effort concentré.
If you read the letters of Paul in the Bible,
Si vous lisez les lettres de Paul dans la Bible,
you will see the concentration of it:
vous en verrez la concentration:
"You go there and you go there and establish a church and do this"
"Vous y allez et vous y allez et établissez une église et faites ceci"
and "What you have done?". Very organized, very systematic,
et "Qu'est-ce que vous avez fait?". Très organisé, très systématique,
absolutely moving like a belt on a machine.
bouger absolument comme une ceinture sur une machine.
And they all the time have that after effects of that movement.
Et ils ont tout le temps cet après effets de ce mouvement.
Charlie Chaplin has shown in his picture "Modern Times".
Charlie Chaplin a montré dans sa photo "Modern Times".
I used to enjoy that very much,
J'aimais beaucoup ça,
that he used to tie up a belt, you see, standing
qu'il avait l'habitude d'attacher une ceinture, vous voyez, debout
for about an hour, and then
pendant environ une heure, puis
after some time when he was released of the job,
après un certain temps quand il a été libéré de son travail,
he used to go on like that.
il avait l'habitude de continuer comme ça.
That kind of an attention,
Ce genre d'attention,
that is concentrated, means stuck onto something.
qui est concentré, signifie collé sur quelque chose.
It's not that, it's not penetrating.
Ce n'est pas ça, ce n'est pas pénétrant.
Because if your attention doesn't become, by concentration,
Parce que si votre attention ne devient pas, par concentration,
subtler and subtler, then it is not that
subtil et subtil, alors ce n'est pas que
but it is getting stuck, and the stuck attention
mais il se coince, et l'attention reste bloquée
is of no use for Sahaja Yoga.
est d'aucune utilité pour Sahaja Yoga.
Such people, I do not know, will never be saved perhaps.
Je ne sais pas, de telles personnes ne seront peut-être jamais sauvées.
So called successful.
Donc appelé réussi.
They'll go with all their badges, everything,
Ils iront avec tous leurs badges, tout,
and God will say, "Go back gentlemen,
et Dieu dira: "Retournez messieurs,
you are not yet been passed through the customs."
vous n'êtes pas encore passé à la douane. "
There is another organization,
Il y a une autre organisation,
which works much faster, much smarter way,
qui fonctionne beaucoup plus rapidement, de manière beaucoup plus intelligente,
and a very specially efficient thing.
et une chose très efficace.
So these people will be just 'stuck' people.
Donc, ces gens seront juste des gens «coincés».
Now there are fourth type of people which are concentrated.
Maintenant, il y a un quatrième type de personnes qui sont concentrées.
They are intense, deep.
Ils sont intenses, profonds.
They penetrate
Ils pénètrent
because they are living minds.
parce qu'ils sont des esprits vivants.
Theirs are not dead, parched minds, they have living mind,
Ils ne sont pas des esprits morts et assoiffés, ils ont un esprit vivant,
they penetrate.
ils pénètrent.
I watch sometimes, I ask some people
Je regarde parfois, je demande à certaines personnes
what do you think of a particular person?
que pensez-vous d'une personne en particulier?
Immediately I know, what they talk.
Immédiatement, je sais de quoi ils parlent.
If they just talk in a mundane way,
S'ils parlent simplement d'une manière banale,
"He is a fine person, he is a bad person, this thing, that thing",
"C'est une personne bien, c'est une personne mauvaise, cette chose, cette chose"
then I know what it is. Very superficial, shallow.
alors je sais ce que c'est. Très superficiel, peu profond.
But a person who sees the possibilities and the potentialities of
Mais une personne qui voit les possibilités et les potentialités de
it's awakening, and the problems a person is facing,
il se réveille et les problèmes auxquels une personne est confrontée,
then I know that he is the one who has that concentration
then I know that he is the one who has that concentration
into the subject.
into the subject.
And the subject of Sahaja Yoga requires the maximum,
And the subject of Sahaja Yoga requires the maximum,
maximum, penetration, because Sahaja Yoga,
maximum, penetration, because Sahaja Yoga,
if you have understood, I don't know if you have understood
if you have understood, I don't know if you have understood
or you are aware of it or not,
or you are aware of it or not,
but is learned through experience and through nothing else.
but is learned through experience and through nothing else.
You have to experience and then believe into it.
You have to experience and then believe into it.
It is not that what I told you is a conditioning on your mind,
It is not that what I told you is a conditioning on your mind,
nothing, you experience it yourself and learn.
nothing, you experience it yourself and learn.
But those who have that penetrating intelligence,
But those who have that penetrating intelligence,
who have that penetrating love, emotions
who have that penetrating love, emotions
and those [who] have that penetrating movement
and those [who] have that penetrating movement
of their understanding,
of their understanding,
they are the ones who experience, learn, experience,
they are the ones who experience, learn, experience,
learn, experience, learn.
learn, experience, learn.
They do not allow their mind to play on them,
They do not allow their mind to play on them,
"No, no, no.
"No, no, no.
This mind of mine has got experiences of the past,
This mind of mine has got experiences of the past,
and is based on that. No, I have to take everyday
and is based on that. No, I have to take everyday
a new experience
a new experience
and that experience must be silenced within me,
and that experience must be silenced within me,
must be sustained within me,
must be sustained within me,
must be conditioned within me."
must be conditioned within me."
Sahaja Yoga experiences are the good conditionings,
Sahaja Yoga experiences are the good conditionings,
"How can it be? I've seen it,
"How can it be? I've seen it,
I have faced it, I've had it. How can it be?".
I have faced it, I've had it. How can it be?".
But for that also, to have the best experiences,
But for that also, to have the best experiences,
first condition is of Rutambhara Pragnya,
first condition is of Rutambhara Pragnya,
where you should be of that level
where you should be of that level
that you really get those experiences,
that you really get those experiences,
otherwise you'll be just a mundane type of a person all the time,
otherwise you'll be just a mundane type of a person all the time,
and you may live with Me,
and you may live with Me,
but you will not have those experiences,
but you will not have those experiences,
you'll not have that blissful feeling,
you'll not have that blissful feeling,
nothing, that joy.
nothing, that joy.
So this penetration starts by your meditation
So this penetration starts by your meditation
and sustenance of the meditation,
and sustenance of the meditation,
and the Samadhi seed sprouting,
and the Samadhi seed sprouting,
manifesting the new dimension within.
manifesting the new dimension within.
This sort of an attention, one has to develop,
This sort of an attention, one has to develop,
by watching the attention, Chitta Nirodha.
by watching the attention, Chitta Nirodha.
As you watch your money,
As you watch your money,
as you watch your road when you drive,
as you watch your road when you drive,
as you watch your child when it is growing,
as you watch your child when it is growing,
as you watch the beauty of your wife,
as you watch the beauty of your wife,
or the care of your husband.
or the care of your husband.
All put together, you watch yourself, your attention,
All put together, you watch yourself, your attention,
where is it going?
where is it going?
Where is it lagging behind?
Where is it lagging behind?
What is happening to my attention?
What is happening to my attention?
Such people have no problems.
Such people have no problems.
You'll be surprised, that such people
You'll be surprised, that such people
when they want to do something it becomes dynamic.
when they want to do something it becomes dynamic.
They can work it out. Nobody has any problem,
They can work it out. Nobody has any problem,
and if there is a problem,
and if there is a problem,
which you are facing all the time,
which you are facing all the time,
in you then know there is something wrong with you.
in you then know there is something wrong with you.
Something is wrong with the instrument.
Something is wrong with the instrument.
If you don't have a tin cutter
If you don't have a tin cutter
and you start using a knife to cut a tin, doesn't work out.
and you start using a knife to cut a tin, doesn't work out.
Then you'll say, "The tin is, something wrong with the tin",
Then you'll say, "The tin is, something wrong with the tin",
or something wrong with you?
or something wrong with you?
No, it's wrong with the instrument
No, it's wrong with the instrument
and that instrument has to be corrected.
and that instrument has to be corrected.
When the instrument is all right,
When the instrument is all right,
after all, with all the powers you have,
after all, with all the powers you have,
with all the blessings you have,
with all the blessings you have,
and the source of power behind it,
and the source of power behind it,
everything should work out. It should work out.
everything should work out. It should work out.
You have had experiences of things working out.
You have had experiences of things working out.
You have had experiences
You have had experiences
of many of miracles happening before your eyes,
of many of miracles happening before your eyes,
but still the attention has not settled down
but still the attention has not settled down
with those experiences. Still 'gatanubhavas'
with those experiences. Still 'gatanubhavas'
means the old experiences continue.
means the old experiences continue.
Old identifications continue.
Old identifications continue.
You still continue with that
You still continue with that
and the filth of that is still on your being.
and the filth of that is still on your being.
Change everything.
Change everything.
Become a fresh new person.
Become a fresh new person.
You are blooming out as a flower
You are blooming out as a flower
and then as a tree
and then as a tree
and assume your position.
and assume your position.
Assume your position as the Sahaj yogi.
Assume your position as the Sahaj yogi.
So this attention must be brought round.
So this attention must be brought round.
You judge yourself, where is your attention
You judge yourself, where is your attention
and what is the point of understanding?
and what is the point of understanding?
What is the measure of understanding?
What is the measure of understanding?
It's very simple: I have to be pleased.
It's very simple: I have to be pleased.
Because I'm the attention.
Because I'm the attention.
If I am pleased then you have done the job.
If I am pleased then you have done the job.
But I cannot be pleased by mundane things,
But I cannot be pleased by mundane things,
by any arguments with that, but only by your ascent.
by any arguments with that, but only by your ascent.
So you judge yourself on that.
So you judge yourself on that.
Whether you give Me a flower,
Whether you give Me a flower,
or anything
or anything
I'm only pleased when the essence of that doing
I'm only pleased when the essence of that doing
has that height, has that special manifestation.
has that height, has that special manifestation.
You say, "I love you very much Mother."
You say, "I love you very much Mother."
All right, you say,
All right, you say,
but I must see that love that you are saying,
but I must see that love that you are saying,
or doing, has that essence that gives Me joy.
or doing, has that essence that gives Me joy.
It's such a mutual thing between us, you can't imagine.
It's such a mutual thing between us, you can't imagine.
I can't live without you and you can't live without Me.
I can't live without you and you can't live without Me.
It's so mutual.
It's so mutual.
But from one side
But from one side
it is absolutely hundred per cent benevolent.
it is absolutely hundred per cent benevolent.
Whether I get angry with you, whether I scold you,
Whether I get angry with you, whether I scold you,
whether I pamper you, whether I say, "Don't do that."
whether I pamper you, whether I say, "Don't do that."
If I tell you, "Don't come very close to Me. Keep away",
If I tell you, "Don't come very close to Me. Keep away",
anything that I do like that, is benevolent
anything that I do like that, is benevolent
to you.
to you.
And to Me the benevolence is only one,
And to Me the benevolence is only one,
that you should be emancipated,
that you should be emancipated,
that you should gain something out of Me,
that you should gain something out of Me,
that you should prosper out of Me.
that you should prosper out of Me.
Like the Mother Earth feels so elated
Like the Mother Earth feels so elated
to see Her manifestation into these beautiful green trees,
to see Her manifestation into these beautiful green trees,
it's like that. She's nothing. We stand on Her, we walk on Her.
it's like that. She's nothing. We stand on Her, we walk on Her.
Where do we see Her? But She sees us, in those.
Where do we see Her? But She sees us, in those.
It's a same sort of a situation.
It's a same sort of a situation.
She is the one who changes all the seasons.
She is the one who changes all the seasons.
'Rutambhara' means the one, the attention,
'Rutambhara' means the one, the attention,
which changes the seasons. 'Rutu' means the seasons.
which changes the seasons. 'Rutu' means the seasons.
So all the seasons are created by Her
So all the seasons are created by Her
just to please us.
just to please us.
But what do we do, to please Her?
But what do we do, to please Her?
We exhaust Her, torture Her,
We exhaust Her, torture Her,
take out everything from Her, pollute it,
take out everything from Her, pollute it,
do all kinds of nonsensical things,
do all kinds of nonsensical things,
and then She gets angry.
and then She gets angry.
The same thing that She is Love.
The same thing that She is Love.
In the same love She becomes angry,
In the same love She becomes angry,
and then you have volcanoes, and you have earthquakes,
and then you have volcanoes, and you have earthquakes,
and all kinds of things happening to you.
and all kinds of things happening to you.
But of course your Mother takes time to get angry.
But of course your Mother takes time to get angry.
Takes time. That doesn't mean you take time.
Takes time. That doesn't mean you take time.
Look after yourselves, it's very important.
Look after yourselves, it's very important.
Suddenly you will find elevated.
Suddenly you will find elevated.
Some people will just elevate themselves
Some people will just elevate themselves
and others will be completely cut out.
and others will be completely cut out.
So be careful, I'm warning.
So be careful, I'm warning.
So today is the day, previous day to this fifteenth day.
So today is the day, previous day to this fifteenth day.
And the fourteenth day, one has to become a killer.
And the fourteenth day, one has to become a killer.
Killer of all that is ignorance,
Killer of all that is ignorance,
of all that is stupid, idiotic,
of all that is stupid, idiotic,
all that is cunning and all that is emotional.
all that is cunning and all that is emotional.
Kill that part, become a Sahaja Yogi,
Kill that part, become a Sahaja Yogi,
tomorrow, to receive the blessings.
tomorrow, to receive the blessings.
May God Bless you.
May God Bless you.